"Green Tea as a Mouthwash
for Halitosis (Bad Breath)"
Tea is the second most widely
consumed beverage in the world,
after water, to the tune of
billions of pounds every year.
In my last video I showed
how drinking green tea
after eating garlic
helps deodorize your breath.
But what about drinking
green tea
to deodorize regular bad breath
without the garlic?
There's been a lot of studies
on the effect of green tea
on other aspects
of oral health.
For example, green tea
appears to work as well
as chlorhexidine
for reducing plaque,
and chlorhexidine
is like the gold standard.
Green tea is safer too.
Chlorhexidine has
so many side effects
you're not supposed to use
if for more than
a short time period;
side effects like discoloration
of the teeth,
increased formation of tartar,
an impairment
of taste sensation,
and occasionally damage
to the inner lining
of your mouth,
whereas if anything,
drinking green tea
appears to have
good side effects.
Tea consumption is associated
with living a longer life
thanks to links
to less cardiac death,
heart disease, stroke,
and type 2 diabetes-
and not just by a little.
A three cup (720 ml)
a day increase
in tea consumption per day
is associated with
a 24 percent decreased risk
of premature death
from all causes put together,
the equivalent of adding
about two years
onto your lifespan.
The longevity link extends
to both green tea and black,
though the per cup effect
appears greater with green.
If you compare
the anti-microbial efficacy
of green tea and chlorhexidine
mouth rinses
against the bacteria
associated with tooth decay
in children with severe
early childhood cavities,
this study found
that a green tea mouth rinse
was superior to chlorhexidine,
but this study
found the opposite.
Chlorhexidine wiped out
like 95 percent
of the decay bacteria,
versus more like 70 percent
for green tea,
but just rinsing
with water alone
can cut levels in half.
So, in terms of
protecting teeth,
the effectiveness of green tea
as a mouth rinse agent
has not been proven.
But what about for bad breath?
The effect of green tea
on halitosis
has evidently been well known
from early times,
perhaps due
to the deodorizing activity
of certain
antioxidant polyphenols.
But you don't really know
until you put it to the test.
This study found that sucking
on green tea tablets
reduced stinky breath compounds,
but who sucks on tea tablets?
Here, green tea was compared
to breath mints, chewing gum,
and parsley oil,
and green tea seemed to help,
but did not reach
statistical significance.
But again, it wasn't drinking
or swishing with green tea,
but rather
some green tea powder
sprinkled on people's tongues.
This study used actual tea
and found
that one minute later,
swishing with green tea
was no better
than swishing with water.
Okay, but what about chronic use
over time?
This is the study
I had been looking for.
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
in which people
rinsed their mouths twice a day
for a month
with a green tea mouthwash
or a similar looking/tasting
placebo mouthwash.
And at the end of the month,
the stinky bad breath compounds
were reduced nearly 40 percent
in the green tea group versus
closer to only 10 percent
in the placebo group.
Bottom line:
a systematic review
on the effect of the tea plant
on decreasing
the level of halitosis
concluded
that green tea mouthwash
can indeed reduce bad breath,
though they don't feel
the evidence
is sufficiently robust
for dentists
to start recommending it
on its own
due to lack of enough
randomized clinical studies.
But green tea mouthwash can be
a good treatment of choice
beside other halitosis
treatments,
like tongue scraping,
to achieve
better clinical results.